To use git you should install it first
If you are on linux you can just use your package manager.
No matter what package manager it is they can all install git.
You can use the most default setup, no customization is needed
running "git" command on Mac will make it install xcode tools
that contain git as well, but its version is not the latest.
Theres also an official package that you can download from the git website,
but it might not be the latest as well.
Most of the time it doesnt matter as even old git will let be able to handle most of the tasks you need.
But if we want to use the latest and greatest
then its either a Homebrew or a MacPorts.
All the default settings will do as modern installers mostly have optimal settings in place already.
Of course you'll be able to change them later, but 99% of the time defaults will have all your needs covered.